Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Historical Society oral history program interviews
1999-2016
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Historical Society
SC0932
16793.6 megabyte(s)
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Scope and Contents note
The Stanford Historical Society's Oral History Program explores the institutional history of the University, with an emphasis on the transformative post-WWII period, through interviews with leading faculty, staff, alumni, trustees, and others. The project furthers the Society's mission "to foster and support the documentation, study, publication, and preservation of the history of the Leland Stanford Junior University."
Like any primary source material, oral history is not intended to present the final, verified, or complete narrative of events. It is a unique, reflective, spoken account, offered by the interviewee in response to questioning, and as such it may be deeply personal. By capturing the flavor of incidents, events, and personalities, the oral history approach provides details and viewpoints that are not often found in traditional records.
Transcripts in this collection are lightly edited by program staff and by Interviewees to correct grammar and occasional inaccuracies. Audio, however, is not edited. As a result, transcripts do not match recordings verbatim.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in nine series: Series 1. Alumni Interviews; Series 2. Artists Interviews; Series 3. Athletics Hall of Fame Project; Series 4. Diversity Project Interviews; Series 5. Faculty and Staff Interviews; Series 6. Founding Grant Project Interviews; Series 7. Peace Corps 50th Anniversary Oral History Project; Series 8. Stanford Presidential Families Project; Series 9. Stanford Arts Initiative Project.
Stanford University -- Faculty.; College students -- California -- Stanford.; Stanford University -- Students.; Stanford University -- Alumni -- Reminiscences.; Diversity in the workplace -- California.; Stanford University -- Administration.; Packer, Nancy Huddleston; Stanford Historical Society; Wolff, Tobias; Underdall, Jerry.; Bishop, Jonathan; Farrar, William R.; Coblentz, Jean; Plunkett, Judith Sterling.; Schwartz, John J.; Carson, Clayborne, 1944-; Chanowitz, Alice Supton; Eddelman, William Smiley, III.; Hamburg, David A.; Ransohoff, Jim; Pewthers, Don; Rea, Jay Weston; Ray, James; Rehmus, Frederick P.; Lyons, James W.; Regan, Joe; Ritchie, Milton Hoke; Kirst, Michael W.; Rensselaer, Cortlandt Van; Knoles, George Harmon; Ogletree, Charles; Maccoby, Eleanor Emmons; Newell, Dr. J.; McAndrews, Rosemary; Oliveira, Nathan; Peatman, Angela Brovelli; Moulton, Bob.; Parker, George; Miller, Arjay R.; Pewthers, Carole; Petriceks, Juris; Schofield, Susan.; Ramsaur, Michael F.; Serlin, Michael; Severin, Charlotte Wood; Smead, Frank; Nix, William D.; Smith, Marilyn; Spaeth, C. Grant; Shah, Haresh C.; Ryan, Lawrence V.; Schimke, Robert T.; Robertson, Sandy; Traugott, Elizabeth C.; Stanford University. Class of 1957; Rodgers, Joseph L.; Roodhouse, Jim; Sheehan, James J.; Ross, Elizabeth Boardman; Ruehl, Sonya Hamburg; Ames, Robert H. Piestewa; Sandke, Terry; Voll, Peter R.; Sawyer, Robert; Tissot, Paula; Adams, James L.; Telleen, Marjorie Horcuitz; Arrow, Kenneth Joseph; Telleen, L. Sherman.; Turner, Paul Venable; Anderson, T. W. (Theodore Wilbur), 1918-; Triolo, James; Andreopoulos, Spyros.; Trego, Charlotte Limoges; Tracy, Else Peters; Chowning, John M.; Stine, Sharon; Barnes, Arthur P.; Steinhart, John; Staudt, David; Lyman, Jing; Corn, Wanda M.; Suppes, Patrick; DeBra, Daniel B.; Straley, Rosemary George; Falcon, Walter P.; Stone, Willfred; Whittier, Mary Ann Van Berckelaer; Wells, Edwin A.; Whitney, Carol; Fong, Herb.; Feigenbaum, Edward A.; Fuchs, Victor R.; Walters, Dorothy Jane Kidd; Walters, James D.; Vincenti, Walter G.; Harvey, Van Austin; Voss, David; Gibbons, James F.; Wells, Alison Dice; Wells, David; Herrington, Marvin L.; Walton, Ann; Kelley, David Michael; Welch, Michael; Fialer, Phil; Fetter, Jane; Farrar, Nancy L.; Falchi, John P.; Ely, Leonard W.; Dunlap, Jim; Duff-Brown, Beth; Doty, Andrew M.; Hastorf, Albert H.; Harris, Larry; Hancock, John; Hamrdla, G. Robert.; Guertin, Richard; Gray, Sharon Harris; Flattery, Tom; Flattery, Annette; Cannell, Roger; Lynch, John.; Ching, Wilton; Butler, Lew; Butler, Suzanne; Bunnell, John; Bushnell, Kay; Brown, Mary Karen Simmons; Holub, Leo; Brown, Walter; Dodge, Judith; Dong, Nelson; Der, Henry.; Docter, Stephen D.; Consear, Pam; Dawson, Don; McDonald, Marilyn Miller; McCraw, William; Robinson, Norman W.; McNair-Knox, Faye; Porras, Jerry I.; McIntyre, Bob; Rosenzweig, Robert M.; Lobdell, Frank; Kojiro, Dan; Maveety, Patrick J.; Mast, Jack; Leckie, James O.; Mitchell, David W.; Bienenstock, Artie; Mitchell, Carol Clifford; Narver, Ellen; Mukoyama, Wesley; Gibbs, James Lowell; Menlove, Frances; Abernethy, David B.; Mellini, Peter; Miller, William F.; Messner, Hal; Burciaga, Cecilia Preciado; Humberg, Judith L.; Inderbitzen, Anton L.; Ingram, Barbara; Jedenoff, George A.; Hill, Patricia; Hoagland, Laurie; Horley, Al; Kiefer, William C.; Krupp, Marcus; Le, Yen; Leonard, Jean McCarter; Kahn, Matt; Shockley, Hillary.; Keating, Ralph; Kennedy, Jeanne; Woodward, Denni.; Carnochan, W. B.; Street, Robert L.; Nogales, Luis G.; Lewenstein, Marion; Stansky, Peter; Young, Ernle W. D.; Stone, Wilfred Healy; Alfaro, Susan Brady; Audrain, Calvert; Anderson, James T.; Bacon, Mary Montle; Bacchetti, Raymond F.; Bark, Dennis; Lundblade, Frederick Hubert.; Ballinger, Delphi; Brown, Jackie.; Bishop, Jonathan; Cohen, Albert; Smith, Thorn.; Bays, Jerry; Kennedy, Donald; Nordling, Martha.; Boyd, Harold K.; Griffin-Jones, Mary M.; Booker, Jayne; Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982; Turner, Marshall C.; Rebholz, R.A. (Ronald A.); Simoni, Robert D.; Bramcamp, Julie Olson; Sunshine, Philip; Bradley, Judith Lynn; Richter, Burton; Gelpi, Barbara Charlesworth.; Sher, Byron D.; Olkin, Ingram; Quinn, Helen R.; Gelpi, Albert.; Raffel, Sidney; Merigan, Thomas C.; Milton, Catherine H.; Leiderman, P. Herbert; Litt, Iris F.; McCarty, Perry L.; Kraemer, Helena C.; Katchadourian, Herant A.; Kays, William M.; Efron, Bradley; Ehrlich, Paul R.; Herzenberg, Leonore A.; Chase, Robert A.; Holman, Halsted R.; Donaldson, Sarah S.; Degler, Carl N.
- Alumni Interviews, 1999-2009; Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a videocassette and audiocassette of the alumni reunion session held on Oct. 14, 1999; audio recordings and transcripts of interviews with alumni from the class of 1957 done during the class reunions held on campus during the fall quarter, 2007; and audio recordings and transcripts of the Alumni Stories project.
  The Alumni Stories project was piloted during Reunion Homecoming Weekend in October 2007, and was repeated in October 2008. Over 60 alumni, most attending their 50th reunions, recounted their memories and stories about undergraduate student life in the 1950s. An additional 15 alumni were interviewed at a Founding Grant Society event in 2009.
  - Reunion session, 1999 Oct 14; Accession ARCH-2001-310; 1 videotape (digital); 1 audiocassette (Box 1)
  - Alumni Stories, 2007; Accession ARCH-2009-056
    - Interview list [all class of 1957] and indexes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alfaro, Susan Brady, 2007
    - Anderson, James T., 2007
    - Bramcamp, Julie Olson, 2007
    - Brown, Mary Karen Simmons, 2007
    - Brown, Walter, 2007
    - Cannell, Roger, 2007
    - Falchi, John P., 2007
    - Gray, Sharon Harris, 2007
    - Inderbitzen, Anton L., 2007
    - Leonard, Jean McCarter, 2007
    - McGraw, William, 2007
    - McDonald, Marilyn Miller, 2007
    - Mitchell, Carol Clifford, 2007
    - Mitchell, David W., 2007
    - Peatman, Angela Brovelli, 2007
    - Petriceks, Juris, 2007
    - Rea, Jay Weston, 2007
    - Ruehl, Sonya Hamburg, 2007
    - Sawyer, Robert, 2007
    - Serlin, Michael, 2007
    - Stine, Sharon, 2007
    - Tracy, Else Peters, 2007
    - Walters, Dorothy Jane Kidd and Walters, James D., 2007 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Whittier, Mary Ann Van Berckelaer, 2007
    - Interviews with Susan Alfaro, James Anderson, Julie Bramcamp, 2007; 2007.1; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Interviews with Mary Brown, Walter Brown, Roger Cannell, 2007; 2007.2; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Interviews with John Falchi, Sharon Gray, Anton Inderbitzen, Jean Leonard, 2007; 2007.3; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Interviews with Marilyn McDonald, William McGraw, 2007.4; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Interviews with Carol Mitchell, David Mitchell, Angela Peatman, 2007; 2007.5; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Interviews with Juris Petriceks, Jay Weston Rea, Sonya Ruehl, 2007; 2007.6; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Interviews with Robert Sawyer, Michael Serlin, Sharon Stine, 2007; 2007.7; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Interviews with Else Peters Tracy, Dottie Kidd Walters, Jim Walters, 2007; 2007.8; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Interview with Mary Ann Whittier, 2007; 2007.9; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Audio files; raw transcripts, 2 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Alumni Stories, 2008
    - Audrain, Calvert
    - Ballinger, Delphi, 2008 Oct 9
    - Bays, Jerry, 2008 Oct 9
    - Bushnell, Kay, 2008 Oct 9
    - Ching, Wilton, 2008 Oct 11
    - Dawson, Don, 2008 Oct 10
    - Dodge, Judith, 2008 Oct 11
    - Dunlap, Jim, 2008 Oct 10
    - Fetter, Jane, 2008 Oct 9
    - Fialer, Phil, 2008 Dec 5
    - Flattery, Annette
    - Flattery, Tom, 2008 Oct 9
    - Hancock, John, 2008
    - Harris, Larry, 2008 Oct 10
    - Hill, Patricia, 2008 Oct 12
    - Hoagland, Laurie, 2008 Oct 9
    - Ingram, Barbara
    - Jedenoff, George A., 2008 Oct 27
    - Keating, Ralph, 2008 Nov 21
    - Krupp, Marcus, 2008 Oct 12
    - McIntyre, Bob
    - Mast, Jack, 2008 Oct 9
    - Mellini, Peter, 2008 Oct 9
    - Menlove, Frances, 2008 Oct 10
    - Messner, Hal, 2008 Oct 11
    - Newell, Dr. J., 2008 Nov 18
    - Pewthers, Don and Pewthers, Carole, 2008 Oct 31
    - Ransohoff, Jim, 2008 Oct 12
    - Ray, James & Wells, David, 2008
    - Regan, Joe, 2008 Oct 10
    - Roodhouse, Jim, 2008 Oct 10
    - Ross, Elizabeth Boardman, 2008
    - Sandke, Terry, 2008 Oct 9
    - Severin, Charlotte Wood
    - Smead, Frank, 2008 Oct 10
    - Smith, Marilyn, 2008 Oct 10
    - Staudt, David, 2008 Oct 12
    - Staudt, David and Ross, Elizabeth Boardman
    - Tissot, Paula, 2008 Oct 9
    - Trego, Charlotte Limoges
    - Triolo, James, 2008 Oct 12
    - Vincenti, Walter, 2008 Oct 9
    - Walton, Ann
    - Whitney, Carol
  - Fialer, Phil, 2008 Dec 5
  - Griffin-Jones, Mary M., 2010 May 19
    Scope and Contents
    The interview with Dr. Mary Murray-Griffin-Jones covered several topics and even included a few photos from her experience of Stanford University. She explained her family’s long-time connection to the university, including a photograph of her grandfather Augustus Taber Murray, who was an early faculty member of the Classics Department. Dr. Murray-Griffin-Jones told stories about her time as an undergraduate and a medical student at Stanford, describing some of her classmates, classes, and social activities. Finally, she reflected on her participation in the Stanford community after graduation, especially in the Stanford Founding Grant Society.
  - Lokey, Lorry I., 2011-04-07
    Lorry I. Lokey, Stanford alumnus and a major philanthropist, discusses the founding of Business Wire, its growth and success. He was a student in Stanford’s Department of Communication and a former editor of The Stanford Daily. His Stanford education had an important impact on his life and perspectives. He was a pioneer in the news service business. Many of his donations went to Stanford with the largest being the Lorry I. Lokey Stem Cell Research Building. His philanthropy is wide ranging but centers on universities and other schools.
  - Nordling, Martha, 2010 Dec 9
    Biographical / Historical
    Martha Nordling Eakland was a member of the Class of '41. In spite of her wish to attend UCLA with her friends, the head of the English department at Los Angeles High School and her father got her to Stanford. What followed was a wonderful education enriched by friendships, sports, memorable professors and escapades. She was the president of Women's Council, and she played in Stanford’s first intramural women’s basketball game against University of California-Berkeley.
  - Smith, Thorn, 2012 Sep 8
    Thorn Smith is a retired fisheries and endangered species attorney. On his graduation from Stanford, he started a diving company in Morro Bay, California and spent about 10 years as a commercial diver. He developed an interest in marine affairs and then marine biology and so he went to law school. He was hired to be a Fisheries attorney for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Washington, DC. Eventually, he became involved in the very early implementation of the Magnuson Fishery Conservation and Management Act of 1976. It was the beginning of a huge period of development in marine science, technology and commercial fisheries.
    After five years as a federal fishery manager and attorney, he moved to Seattle which was the hub of American fisheries, offshore fisheries, and represented different groups for the rest of my career. Thorn Smith served on a couple of committees where he worked on issues related to international fisheries and endangered species. He also spent a lot of time lobbying on Capitol Hill relating to fisheries.
    In 1961, Thorn Smith was one of three delegates sent by Stanford's Beta Chi chapter to Sigma Nu national fraternity's annual convention. The delegation was charged with trying to get the convention to vote to repeal a clause in the national fraternity's 1868 charter, which forbade membership to people of African descent. Smith and his fellow petitioners were not given a hearing and felt it was clear they were recognized when they asked to speak because the national fraternity had no wish to open discussion of the matter. In November, 1962, the Stanford chapter seceded from the national fraternity in protest of its policy of racial exclusion. Smith recalls his experience leading up to the national convention, being responded to with intense anger at the convention, and the subsequent act of secession. The interview provides insight into the early development of political activism on the Stanford campus in the 1960s.
  - Turner, Marshall C., 2012 Sep 20
    In 1959, a year after one member ran over and killed another in the driveway on Big Game Bonfire night, the Beta Chi (Stanford) chapter of Sigma Nu national fraternity was near collapse. A number of freshmen got together in 1960 and pledged the fraternity as a group. They aimed at a diverse pledge class, comprised of as many of the leaders of the class of 1963 as they could attract. It proved to be an unusual fraternity, boasting among its 1963 graduates two Rhodes Scholars, two Wilsons, two Danforths. Along the way, in November, 1962, the chapter seceded from the national fraternity in protest of its policy of racial exclusion. Marshall Turner describes the assembling of the pledge class and the events that led to its departure from the national. The interview provides insight into the early development of political activism on the Stanford campus in the 1960s.
    Marshall C. Turner is a former CEO or interim CEO of four technology companies and one broadcasting station. His technology industry experience also includes twenty years as a venture capital fund principal, and an early career as an industrial designer and biomedical engineer. Public and community service has been an important aspect of his life. He has chaired the boards of two national organizations – the Smithsonian’s National Museum of Natural History, and the Corporation for Public Broadcasting -- as well as his local school board and public broadcasting station. He has served as a board member of thirty-four organizations -- including twenty-two public or private companies in software, electronics, biotechnology, computer, telecommunication, consumer product, and education markets.
    He is currently a member of three public-company and three non-profit boards of directors: Alliance Bernstein Funds, New York (mutual fund family); MEMC Electronic Materials, Inc., St. Peters, Missouri (semiconductor and solar substrates, solar power plants); Xilinx, Inc., San Jose, California (programmable logic semiconductors); American Alliance of Museums, Washington DC; George Lucas Educational Foundation, Nicasio, California; Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History, Washington DC. During his early career, he gained product design experience at Mattel and General Motors, and then served at the National Institutes of Health as a Commissioned Officer in the U.S. Public Health Service. While a biomedical engineer at NIH, he and a heart surgeon colleague designed an implantable left ventricular heart assist pump, and co-led the team that tested the device through twenty-nine calf implant surgeries, and published several papers on their work.
    Mr. Turner was selected one of 17 White House Fellows in 1970, as he completed his MBA. After his fellowship year as a Special Assistant to Elliot Richardson, then Secretary of Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, he remained in Washington as part of the start-up leadership of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, heading a coordinative staff of MBAs and attorneys reporting to the first Administrator and Deputy Administrator.
    He returned to California in 1973 to begin learning the venture capital business as the associate in a private venture capital firm. Since then, he has been an active technology venture investor based in San Francisco, who often has taken an active leadership role in investments. After co-founding Taylor & Turner Associates, Ltd. in 1981, Mr. Turner was a General Partner managing three related institutional venture capital partnerships through the last one’s completion in 1998. Investments of the firm, and the focus of his subsequent active investing, have been seed and early stage technology-related companies -- usually at their inception.
    His first CEO role was for a small, multinational liquid crystal company that he joined as chairman and CEO at the request of its venture investors, shortly after it filed under Chapter Eleven in 1975. The company was successfully reorganized within a year, then over the next three years grew internationally in medical and consumer markets.
    Mr. Turner served as Chief Executive Officer of Dupont Photomasks, Inc., [symbol DPMI] Austin, Texas, for three years (2003-2006), and chairman while it was a public company. He had also served as a member of the board of directors since the company’s IPO in 1996, and as interim chairman and CEO for eleven months (1999-2000). Photomasks are a key custom component for the fabrication of semiconductor chips. DPI operated through a tightly coupled global network of ten manufacturing sites in Germany, France, China, Korea, Singapore, Taiwan and the United States. Turner was appointed chairman and CEO in June, 2003, following erosion of the company’s operating and financial performance. Operating metrics and financial results strongly improved during his tenure. Then as the company successfully completed a restructuring of its manufacturing network and research laboratories, he led negotiations that resulted in the Company’s acquisition by Toppan Printing Company, Ltd. for $650 million in 2005.
    In 2008-2009, he served as interim CEO of MEMC Electronic Materials, Inc. [symbol WFR], a global manufacturer of silicon wafers for customers in semiconductor and solar power markets with 2008 revenues of $2 billion.
    His public service leadership experience includes membership on the following boards: Smithsonian’s National Museum of Natural History (1997-2006, 2012 to present, chair 2002- 2006 ), the Public Broadcasting Service (1993¬1999, vice-chair 1996-1999); the Corporation for Public Broadcasting (1987-1992, chair 1990-1992); KQED, Inc. in San Francisco (1977- 1983, 1985-1988, chair 1985-1987, interim CEO 1993); and election to the board of trustees of his local school board in California in 1977, which he chaired through major reforms in 1979-1981.
    Mr. Turner received a B.S. Degree in Mechanical Engineering from Stanford University in 1964, and an M.S. Degree in Product Design, a joint program of Stanford's Art and Engineering Departments, in 1965. He was president of his senior class (1963). In 1970, he received an M.B.A. with distinction from Harvard Business School, and received the J. Leslie Rollins Award.
    Mr. Turner is married to Ann Curran Turner, an artist and teacher. They have three adult children.
- Artists Interviews, 2009; Series 2
  - Holub, Leo, 2009 Apr 7, Jun 30
  - Kahn, Matt, 2009 Aug 5
    Biographical/Historical note
    Matt Kahn arrived at Stanford in 1949 at the age of 21. He had been studying at the Cranbrook Academy of Art when then Art and Architecture Department Chair Ray Faulker wrote to Cranbrook for recommendations of someone to teach design as part of Stanford's art curriculum. He has taught at Stanford ever since. Kahn was appointed an assistant professor in 1953, a full professor in 1965, and, in the mid-1960's, along with mechanical engineering Prof. Bob McKim, founded the Joint Program in Design (JPD), with the plan of marrying curricula in design, fine arts and engineering.
    "Constructive disobedience" and "fantasy and soul" are two of Professor Kahn's signature design philosophies and he shares how these approaches have framed his teaching, his personal art-making and many of his class assignments. From his setting up complicated still life scenes for his drawing classes, to his later 'Cyclops' lectures and Art 60 pumpkin carving projects, he shares memories of student reactions, interactions and design experiences.
    Kahn describes how his presence as a designer and artist has been somewhat of an enigma to other art faculty throughout his career and notes how the early days of launching the undergraduate courses and the graduate JPD curriculum has been a gradual merging of engineering and art/design cultures and political/personal perspectives. He briefly remembers the time when he decided not to return to formal collegiate study to obtain a degree.
    Professor Kahn is proud of the professional successes of his former students, among them David Kelley, IDEO founder and former JPD teacher, and Michael Duncan, Director at San Francisco architecture firm Skidmore, Owings & Merrill. Matt talks about Stanford campus – the Quad, in particular – and the many relationships he has developed and maintained with his students and acknowledges how much he learns from and appreciates their presence in his personal and professional lives.
    In this interview, Kahn also remembers his years as a design consultant with Eichler Homes and how his year in Cambodia for the US State Department influenced his own product designs and his design aesthetic.
  - Lobdell, Frank, 2009 Jul
    Oral history interview conducted in July 2009 pertaining to Lobdell's time at Stanford. Topics include building Stanford's studio art program, his association with Nathan Oliveira, Keith Boyle and other artists, and his own approach to art.
    Frank Lobdell came to Stanford University in 1965 as an Artist in Residence; the following year he joined the faculty in the studio art program. In 1989 he was appointed the Paul L. and Phyllis Wattis Professor of Art and retired from that position in 1991.